<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-28T22:09:42+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Radim Oliva</title><entry><title type="html">4</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/27/4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4" /><published>2025-05-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/27/4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/27/4.html"><![CDATA[<p>I was pouring concrete sidewalk next to house today, did a big chunk of it. Did some minor things in the house as well. Drank a lot of caffeine. Throughout most of this I had my earphones and listened to several interviews with founders. The guy who founded Airbnb, Brian Chesky (I just Googled to find out meaning behind the company name, that’s how I know his name, otherwise I wouldn’t remember to save my life), the young fellow who founded Cursor AI, the slightly older man who founded Notion and maybe someone else as well who I can’t recall right now. Is this habit of listening to podcasts just a noise that keeps me company? I am trying to recall some valuable insights from those hours of listening. To be fair I had to aim some of the attention to the concrete pouring. I should probably give the Notion app some more chance. There are so many tools for just about everything. It’s all so overwhelming. I’m still so doubtful in my ability to step out from my shadow. Yeah, so I have doubts. Big deal. I’ve lied today to that fucking doctor at the clinic where I’ve signed up to participate in a clinical trials for cash. She asked If I’ve ever had suicidal thoughts and I said ‘course not. Who the fuck doesn’t have suicidal thoughts? There are such people? Fucking weirdos. Fuck you if you read this by the way, because why not. Back to the topic of me trying to remember what I have been listening to all day… Michael from Cursor believes the future of coding is in logical design rather than being in the trenches of trying to figure out the proper code. I like the sound of that, the crude engineering work being outsourced to the AI agents so that I can focus on the product design itself. He said the company has around 60 employees and Lenny mentioned the ARR makes it the fastest growing company in history. What were the two things Michael would recommend to people who just started using Cursor? I can’t pull it out. At least I remember something from Justin Song whom I’ve listened to on the way to Doksy. It was my third run on his take on encoding. Encoding is turning the consumed information into knowledge. Without it you just have crude memorization (which by itself is useless if you don’t know how to apply the information). The most important parts that I can recall are simplifying, boil down everything into the simplest terms, compare it to what you already know so that you can then properly categorize it, without knowing how the newly acquired information relates to other things and where (what book shelf - the library analogy) it fits in the big picutre your brain will have hard time saving the information for later use. Making analogies is a great way to achieve simplification, comparation and using the information in a practical way greatly enhancing the ability to understand key concepts. I need to learn how to make the analogies cause I probably never made a single one. Shame. Anyway it’s getting late and I need to get some sleep. Later.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was pouring concrete sidewalk next to house today, did a big chunk of it. Did some minor things in the house as well. Drank a lot of caffeine. Throughout most of this I had my earphones and listened to several interviews with founders. The guy who founded Airbnb, Brian Chesky (I just Googled to find out meaning behind the company name, that’s how I know his name, otherwise I wouldn’t remember to save my life), the young fellow who founded Cursor AI, the slightly older man who founded Notion and maybe someone else as well who I can’t recall right now. Is this habit of listening to podcasts just a noise that keeps me company? I am trying to recall some valuable insights from those hours of listening. To be fair I had to aim some of the attention to the concrete pouring. I should probably give the Notion app some more chance. There are so many tools for just about everything. It’s all so overwhelming. I’m still so doubtful in my ability to step out from my shadow. Yeah, so I have doubts. Big deal. I’ve lied today to that fucking doctor at the clinic where I’ve signed up to participate in a clinical trials for cash. She asked If I’ve ever had suicidal thoughts and I said ‘course not. Who the fuck doesn’t have suicidal thoughts? There are such people? Fucking weirdos. Fuck you if you read this by the way, because why not. Back to the topic of me trying to remember what I have been listening to all day… Michael from Cursor believes the future of coding is in logical design rather than being in the trenches of trying to figure out the proper code. I like the sound of that, the crude engineering work being outsourced to the AI agents so that I can focus on the product design itself. He said the company has around 60 employees and Lenny mentioned the ARR makes it the fastest growing company in history. What were the two things Michael would recommend to people who just started using Cursor? I can’t pull it out. At least I remember something from Justin Song whom I’ve listened to on the way to Doksy. It was my third run on his take on encoding. Encoding is turning the consumed information into knowledge. Without it you just have crude memorization (which by itself is useless if you don’t know how to apply the information). The most important parts that I can recall are simplifying, boil down everything into the simplest terms, compare it to what you already know so that you can then properly categorize it, without knowing how the newly acquired information relates to other things and where (what book shelf - the library analogy) it fits in the big picutre your brain will have hard time saving the information for later use. Making analogies is a great way to achieve simplification, comparation and using the information in a practical way greatly enhancing the ability to understand key concepts. I need to learn how to make the analogies cause I probably never made a single one. Shame. Anyway it’s getting late and I need to get some sleep. Later.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embrace Silence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/20/embrace-silence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embrace Silence" /><published>2025-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/20/embrace-silence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/20/embrace-silence.html"><![CDATA[<p>I woke up, did some yoga and went for a walk. It’s cloudy outside and kind of dark. Immediately, almost without thinking, I’ve pulled out my wireless headphones and played a video from my Youtube feed called “Embrace The Silence” or something to that effect, from channel Math Sorcerer. His micro essays on topic of studying and achieving one’s goals have been very helpful to me. This guy is like a coach I’ve never met that will just not give up on me no matter what.<br />
In this one particular video he talked about the power of silence and the fact that most of the time we’re used to some auditory stimulus, be it music, podcasts or audio books. I’m very guilty of this myself. Even though I almost exclusively listen to material that has something to do with achieving one’s goals, improving quality of life, entrepreneurship and things I myself may regard as useful and important, it’s still often just a distraction. I definitely feel more connected when someone is speaking directly into my ears. It feels like I am not alone. I also noticed that I am at my most focused when I work in dead silence. As painful as it is, it really makes me use most of my conginitive capacity to complete whatever task is at hand.<br />
To get back to the video, there I am taking a walk and realizing that the Sorcerer is absolutely right, I should limit the amount I listen to something and when I do I need to really intensely focus on whatever’s being discussed or said. Because otherwise it’s just noise and distraction. It’s all about attention and being present. I’ve heard this a couple of times now, how one of the most important resources we have is our attention. Want to listen to music? Fine, make sure you are paying all the attention to it and enjoy every second. Same goes for a podcast, think about what you’re hearing. If you’re going to work on something then focus on the work. In silence.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I woke up, did some yoga and went for a walk. It’s cloudy outside and kind of dark. Immediately, almost without thinking, I’ve pulled out my wireless headphones and played a video from my Youtube feed called “Embrace The Silence” or something to that effect, from channel Math Sorcerer. His micro essays on topic of studying and achieving one’s goals have been very helpful to me. This guy is like a coach I’ve never met that will just not give up on me no matter what. In this one particular video he talked about the power of silence and the fact that most of the time we’re used to some auditory stimulus, be it music, podcasts or audio books. I’m very guilty of this myself. Even though I almost exclusively listen to material that has something to do with achieving one’s goals, improving quality of life, entrepreneurship and things I myself may regard as useful and important, it’s still often just a distraction. I definitely feel more connected when someone is speaking directly into my ears. It feels like I am not alone. I also noticed that I am at my most focused when I work in dead silence. As painful as it is, it really makes me use most of my conginitive capacity to complete whatever task is at hand. To get back to the video, there I am taking a walk and realizing that the Sorcerer is absolutely right, I should limit the amount I listen to something and when I do I need to really intensely focus on whatever’s being discussed or said. Because otherwise it’s just noise and distraction. It’s all about attention and being present. I’ve heard this a couple of times now, how one of the most important resources we have is our attention. Want to listen to music? Fine, make sure you are paying all the attention to it and enjoy every second. Same goes for a podcast, think about what you’re hearing. If you’re going to work on something then focus on the work. In silence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Monday</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/19/this-monday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Monday" /><published>2025-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/19/this-monday</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/19/this-monday.html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to write out my thoughts but it turns out I don’t have that many thoughts or at least ones worth translating into writing. I have plenty of thoughts, in fact.<br />
It is so incredibly difficult for me to focus on certain tasks like writing and working on projects that I’ love to work on. I’m so used to information consumption that it feels entirely alient to me to actually produce information and generate thoughts, ideas and create projects. Projects of the intellectual kind, that is. I can build things physically, no problem. That isn’t to say that I’m good at building them but I have no difficulty doing any kind of manual labor and I love to craft, woodwork or lay bricks, but man do I find it difficult to sit down and just write something. <br />
This problem needs to be overcome. As I said earlier, it’s exceedingly easy for me to consume information. I love to read and I can read for hours, but it’s time for me to start creating. I’d love to bring few projects into life and I really oughtta learn to sit down and write up whole bunch of text if I ever want to make it a reality. These projects can’t just live inside of my head. First I need to articulate exactly what I want to build, what is the purpose, who is it for and so on. That means writing a considerable amount and thinking deepy about what and how I write. The fact that these words are publicly available is forcing me to think harder, I like that very much. I have no clue if anyone ever reads this beside me but I’d like to think it’s not an absolute drivel.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why force yourself to do something that feels uncomfortable?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a good question, I simply can’t go on living like I do now. Actually I can very easily, but it makes me miserable and I don’t like that very much. I want to create and exert as much effort as I can doing it. I don’t want to work a 9-5 where I just do the same thing day after day and then sit at home and consume. I want to break out of this. The one way to achieve  it is to become a creator. I won’t lie I am desperately trying to take advantage of the current AI boom and figure out how to best utilize it to my advantage. I really do believe it’s of critical value to harness this technology, and whatever it’s going to become in the future, to best of my ability. I don’t want to be left behind of the curve. Many people are still passive and react only very slowly to the changes in technology which give me somewhat of an edge.<br />
Year ago I’ve did a month-long retraining course on programming in Python provided by the Employment bureau. I’ve successfully finished the course and received a certificate and my hope was to become a developer. Sadly I’ve fallen of the tracks very quickly and instead of immersing myself in it I’ve gradually lost momentum and even though I’ve continued to educate myself in coding for a while, eventually I’ve given up completely, mainly because I’ve landed (somewhat unexpectedly) a decent paying job in an unrelated field.<br />
One of the reasons I’ve not followed throught, probably, was the fact that I’ve felt programming, especially back-end programming is just not my strong suit. Even though I did a decent job at the course and I was frankly one of the better students there it’s just not in my DNA to love coding, at least not to such a degree so that I could become exceptional at it.<br />
I want to think of myself as more of a designer. I could come up with various problems to solve and way to solve them but then I’d exhaust myself on trying to figure out the how to translate those ideas into programming logic.<br />
<strong>However</strong>, now when we’re well into the age of AI I think it’s possible for someone like me to leverage this technology and actually make something out of it. I need to figure out what and how, because I don’t actually know. And I will not know until I fucking start building something…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I want to write out my thoughts but it turns out I don’t have that many thoughts or at least ones worth translating into writing. I have plenty of thoughts, in fact. It is so incredibly difficult for me to focus on certain tasks like writing and working on projects that I’ love to work on. I’m so used to information consumption that it feels entirely alient to me to actually produce information and generate thoughts, ideas and create projects. Projects of the intellectual kind, that is. I can build things physically, no problem. That isn’t to say that I’m good at building them but I have no difficulty doing any kind of manual labor and I love to craft, woodwork or lay bricks, but man do I find it difficult to sit down and just write something. This problem needs to be overcome. As I said earlier, it’s exceedingly easy for me to consume information. I love to read and I can read for hours, but it’s time for me to start creating. I’d love to bring few projects into life and I really oughtta learn to sit down and write up whole bunch of text if I ever want to make it a reality. These projects can’t just live inside of my head. First I need to articulate exactly what I want to build, what is the purpose, who is it for and so on. That means writing a considerable amount and thinking deepy about what and how I write. The fact that these words are publicly available is forcing me to think harder, I like that very much. I have no clue if anyone ever reads this beside me but I’d like to think it’s not an absolute drivel.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hello World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/12/welcome-to-my-journal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World" /><published>2025-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/12/welcome-to-my-journal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/12/welcome-to-my-journal.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my first journal entry.</p>

<p>After much deliberation and putting things off into the foggy distant future I have finally decided to create something of a personal website, something I should have done very long time ago, nevertheless here it is. I don’t really have a set goal or idea of what this should be but the fact of making my journal public somehow gives more validity or realness, at least in my mind. I have already began journaling about a year ago, physically with pen and paper, a process which in itself is very satisfying and feels more personal and grounded in reality, however at the beginning of this year I have switched to journaling on a computer almost exclusively because it is just so much faster to write down my thoughts and iterate or edit sentences as I go. 
I have very rarely journaled or written anything before that in my life which is a shame, really, I’ve found it really helps one’s ability to formulate ideas and become more articulate, something Jordan B. Peterson often points out in his lectures and talks. That’s one of my main reasons to write down my thoughts, I want to practice formulating my thoughts and thinking as deeply as I can about each and every one of the words that came on the screen or paper.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my first journal entry.]]></summary></entry></feed>